<chapter id="introduction">
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>
		JBoss BAM is a framework for providing a Business Activity
		Monitoring solution that integrates with existing JBoss
		frameworks to retrieve, render and analyze data that empower
		business knowledge.
	</para>

	<section>
		<title>BAM Overview</title>
		<para>
			The term BAM originally appeared at
			<ulink url="http://www.gartner.com">Gartner, Inc</ulink>
			and came from the need of rendering data into valuable
			real-time information to supervisors, officers and managers
			of different units within an organization. The main goal of
			BAM is to provide real-time summary status of different sets
			of transactions, processes and operations.
		</para>
		<para>
			Data and analytical information empower all sort of
			businesses and BAM aims at fortifying the area to enable
			management layers to derive better informed business
			decisions, quickly address problem areas, and re-structure
			their hierarchies to take full advantage of arising
			opportunities.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>BAM vs BI</title>
		<para>
			There's more or less a common confusion when it comes to
			separating BAM (Business Activity Monitoring) from BI
			(Business Intelligence). This confusion comes from the fact
			the the roots of the two technologies come from the same
			background, however the application of the two technologies
			is radically different.
		</para>

		<section>
			<title>Real-time Vs Historical</title>
			<para>
				BAM processes with real-time data while BI handles
				historical facts. BAM pushes data into display panels or
				dashboards while BI retrieves data from history. In this
				context the output of BAM is a dynamic component
				rendered in a graphical or tabular format indicating the
				state of the data at the time it was invoked, while the
				output of BI is a report that describes facts according
				a specific set of criteria and time frame.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Dynamic Vs Static</title>
			<para>
				As stated earlier, BAM highlights actual facts happening
				in transactions, processes or operational-modes, this
				fact highlights a new option that interacts dynamically
				with other components. BAM becomes dynamic in that
				perspective to integrate with rules engines and trigger
				actions such as a notification event or a corrective
				measurement to the activity. For example a BAM query can
				trigger a notification to the manager if the average
				number of tasks executed by a single resource is higher
				than the limit. BAM could take as well corrective
				measurements such as rolling back a financial
				transaction if the value of this transaction exceeds the
				standard quota. On the BI side none of this flexibility
				is available, BI displays only data that is derived from
				the database and rendered in electronic or hard copy
				format. BI provides the layer of analysis of the past to
				take preventive measurments against tasks in the future.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>JBoss BAM Overview</title>
		<para>
			The JBoss BAM solution currently integrates with
			<ulink url="http://labs.jboss.com/jbossjbpm">
				JBoss jBPM
			</ulink>
			. This solution is designed to provide information by
			directly querying the jBPM database and returning the
			results in a set of graphical formats.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
