<chapter id="reports">
	<title>Reports Engine</title>
	<para>
		The BAM solution integrates a reporting engine that allows end
		users to create their own reports using reporting frameworks and
		integrate the reports into the system to be persisted and
		rendered.
	</para>

	<para>
		The reporting engine job is to expose the data of the system and
		its integrated database into the reporting tool so that reports
		can be built, saved into the system and rendered. This feature
		would allow the same report to be built once and the data can be
		gathered at any point in time and exported into different
		formats such as PDF, XML or HTML.
	</para>

	<para>
		At the current state, the frameworks only supports one reporting
		tool. The engine has already the handlers to integrate
		<ulink url="http://www.jasperforge.org">Jasper Reports</ulink>
		. Future plans of the console plan to integrate advanced
		features of Jasper Reports and more reporting frameworks such as
		<ulink url="www.eclipse.org/birt/">Eclipse BIRT</ulink>
		.
		<note>
			This tutorial provides a tutorial on how to use Jasper
			within the JBoss BAM solution, however it's not meant to be
			a Jasper Reports tutorial.
		</note>
	</para>

	<section id="reports_jasper">
		<title>Jasper Reports - Step By Step Guide</title>
		<para>
			This is a step by step guide on how to build reports using
			<ulink url="http://jasperforge.org/sf/projects/ireport">
				iReport
			</ulink>
			and integrate them into the BAM solution. Prior to starting
			please make sure that you have iReport installed. The
			tutorial is built at the version 2.0.4 of Jasper Reports and
			iReport.
		</para>

		<section>
			<title>Jasper Report Design</title>
			<para>
				The report we are aiming to build has the following
				data:
			</para>
			<figure id="report.design">
				<title>Report Design</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata align="center"
							fileref="images/report-design.jpg" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>Our report contains the following elements:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					Parameters:
					<para>
						We will add the report title parameter to the
						report. This variable is passed on from the
						reporting engine to the report prior to
						rendering.
					</para>
					<figure id="report.parameters">
						<title>Report Parameters</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata align="center"
									fileref="images/report-parameter.jpg" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					Query:
					<para>
						Add in the following query to the report. Select
						<menuchoice>
							<guimenu>Data</guimenu>
							<guimenuitem>Report Query</guimenuitem>
						</menuchoice>
						and type in the following SQL query:
						<para>
							<programlisting>
								select processdef1_.NAME_ as
								proc_def_name, count(processdef1_.NAME_)
								proc_def_count from JBPM_PROCESSINSTANCE
								processins0_, JBPM_PROCESSDEFINITION
								processdef1_ where
								processins0_.PROCESSDEFINITION_=processdef1_.ID_
								group by processdef1_.NAME_
							</programlisting>
						</para>
					</para>
					<figure id="report.query">
						<title>Report Query</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata align="center"
									fileref="images/report-query.jpg" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>
					<para>
						Save your report into a location, we'll use the
						file in the next steps. Make sure that you
						include the design as the report layout
						indicates.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Upload Report</title>
			<para>
				In this section we will upload the report we previously
				built and render the results within the system.
			</para>
			<para>
				Navigate using the console to
				<ulink
					url="http://localhost:8080/bamconsole/ReportList.seam">
					http://localhost:8080/bamconsole/ReportList.seam
				</ulink>
				and click the Create Report Button.

				<figure id="report.list">
					<title>Report List</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center"
								fileref="images/report-list.jpg" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</para>
			<para>
				Upload the report created previously to the system and
				fill in the report data as the figure indicates:
				<figure id="report.fill">
					<title>Report Data</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center"
								fileref="images/report-fill.jpg" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</para>

			<para>
				Your report has been succesfully created
				<figure id="report.created">
					<title>Report Created</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center"
								fileref="images/report-created.jpg" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</para>

			<para>
				You can now download your report in the formats that are
				provided by the system. Currently the system generates
				the reports output in 3 formats (PDF, XHTML, XML) -
				Later versions of the reporting engine will allow the
				generation of different outputs suchs as XLS, ODT, CSV
				and much more.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
