<chapter id="gettingstarted">

  <title>Getting started</title>
  <para>This chapter takes you through the first steps of getting JBoss jBPM and 
  provides the initial pointers to get up and running in no time.</para>
  
  <section id="downloadablesoverview">  
    <title>Downloadables Overview</title>    
    <para>Listed below are the different jBPM packages that are available today. 
	Each of these packages contains one or more downloadable files. Along with each of 
	these files goes a description of its contents and a pointer to any relevant 
	installation instructions if they are available.    </para>
    <para>All downloads described below can be found on 
    <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=70542">the 
    sourceforge jbpm downloads page</ulink>.</para>

    <section id="jpdl3">
      <title>jPDL 3</title>

      <para><ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=70542&amp;package_id=145174">
      Download jBPM jPDL 3 at sourceforge.net</ulink>.  This is the main distribution package containing the 
      core engine and a number of additional modules that you may need to work with jPDL. 
      </para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="jbpm-jpdl-suite.zip"><emphasis role="bold">The jPDL Suite (jbpm-jpdl-suite.zip):</emphasis> 
          The jPDL Suite is an extended runtime that includes the designer and the server.  All of 
          these components are preconfigured to interoperate out-of-the-box.
          If you want to get started with jBPM quickly, this is the file you want to download.
          It contains all the other modules of this package plus the graphical designer in one single 
          download. Extract the zipped archive into a folder of your choice and read the file named 'readme.html'
          for more info and further installation instructions. With this starters kit you can 
          immediately get started with the <xref linkend="tutorial" />.
		  </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para id="jbpm-jpdl.zip"><emphasis role="bold">The jPDL Runtime Engine (jbpm-jpdl.zip):</emphasis>
          The download contains the jBPM core library, documentation and dependent libraries, as well as the
          identity component for actor and group management. To start working with it, extract the archive 
          into a folder of your choice. You will find pointers to the User's Guide and other important
          information resources in the 'readme.html' file in the 'jbpm-&lt;version&gt;' folder.
		  </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    
    <section id="packagejpdlprocessdesigner">    
      <title>jPDL Process Designer</title>     

      <para><ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=70542&amp;package_id=116692">
      The jPDL Suite package contains the jPDL process designer.  You typically will download it in that 
      package. But you can also download JBoss jBPM Process Designer separate at sourceforge.net</ulink>.  The 
      designer is an eclipse plugin and enables you to author your process definitions and to easily deploy them.
      The plug-in is available for download either as a zipped Eclipse feature or as a zipped Eclipse update site. 
      There is no difference in content, the only difference is in the way you have to do the installation.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="jbpm-gpd-site-version.zip"><emphasis role="bold">Eclipse Update Site (jbpm-gpd-site-&lt;version&gt;.zip):</emphasis>
          If you want to be absolutely sure that the designer installation goes smoothly, we recommend to use
          the update site mechanism together with a new Eclipse installation. Of cource the Eclipse version 
          should match the downloaded update site archive. To get started with the designer plugin, follow the instructions
          in the 'readme.html' file included in the archives root folder to succesfully install the GPD.
		  </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para id="jbpm-gpd-feature-version.zip"><emphasis role="bold">Eclipse Feature (jbpm-gpd-feature-&lt;version&gt;.zip):</emphasis>
          If you are tired of each time having to do a fresh Eclipse installation and you are willing to
          cope with some possible issues, you can try the feature download. In this case installation is as
          easy as extracting the archive into your Eclipse installation (make sure the included 'plugins' 
          and 'features' folders end up in the same location of your Eclipse installation) overwriting the
          files and folders with the same name that are possibly already present. This installation is 
          very easy, but you could run into incompatibility issues when you overwrite plugins already present
          in your installation because of other features that you did install. Though they have the same name
          it could happen that the versions of these colliding plugins are not equal, hence the possible
          incompatibilities. The installation instructions are repeated in the 'readme.html' file.
		  </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>The JBoss jBPM project directory</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="mailto:sales@jboss.com?subject=jBPM professional support">professional support</ulink></emphasis>: JBoss is the company that backs this project with professional support, training and consultancy services.</listitem>
      <listitem><emphasis role="bold">user guide</emphasis>: is the document you're reading and serves as the main entry point into the project.</listitem>
      <listitem><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/forum/?group_id=70542">forums</ulink></emphasis>: get in contact with the community, ask questions and discuss jBPM</listitem>
      <listitem><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=JbpmWiki">wiki</ulink></emphasis>: extra information, mostly provided by the community</listitem>
      <listitem><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://jira.jboss.com/jira/secure/BrowseProject.jspa?id=10052">issue tracker</ulink></emphasis>: for submitting bugs and feature requests</listitem>
      <listitem><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=70542">downloads</ulink></emphasis>: sourceforge download page for jBPM</listitem>
      <listitem><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=70542">mailing lists</ulink></emphasis>: mailing lists are used for announcements</listitem>
      <listitem><emphasis role="bold">javadocs</emphasis>: part of the download in the doc/javadoc directory.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  
  <section id="cvsaccess">
    <title>Source code CVS access</title>
    
    <section id="anonymouscvsaccess">
      <title>Anonymous CVS access</title>
      <para>Alternatively, you can get JBoss jBPM from cvs with the following 
      information:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>Connection type: pserver</listitem>
        <listitem>User: anonymous </listitem>
        <listitem>Host: anoncvs.forge.jboss.com</listitem>
        <listitem>Port: 2401 (which is the default)</listitem>
        <listitem>Repository path: /cvsroot/jbpm</listitem>
        <listitem>Label: :pserver:anonymous@anoncvs.forge.jboss.com:/cvsroot/jbpm</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    
    <section id="developercvsaccess">
      <title>Developer CVS access</title>
      <para>To get cvs developer access, you must sign contributors agreement and 
      you need an ssh key.  More information on both can be found on 
      <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=CVSRepository">the JBoss cvs
      repository wiki page</ulink></para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>Connection type: ext over ssh (extssh in eclipse)</listitem>
        <listitem>User: sf.net username or jboss username </listitem>
        <listitem>Host: cvs.forge.jboss.com</listitem>
        <listitem>Port: 2401 (which is the default)</listitem>
        <listitem>Repository path: /cvsroot/jbpm</listitem>
        <listitem>Label: :pserver:anonymous@cvs.forge.jboss.com:/cvsroot/jbpm</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  
</chapter>