<chapter id="architecture">
	<title>Architecture</title>

	<para>
		This chapter aims at describing the architecture of the BAM
		framework
	</para>

	<section id="architectural_diagram">
		<title>Architectural Diagram</title>
		<para>
			This diagram aims at highlighting the main components of the
			JBoss BAM solution. The BAM solution is built using
			<ulink url="http://labs.jboss.com/jbossseam">
				JBoss Seam
			</ulink>
		</para>
		<figure id="bam.architecture.image">
			<title>BAM Architecture</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata align="center"
						fileref="images/bam-architecture.jpg" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</section>

	<section id="components">
		<title>Components</title>
		<para>
			The architecture is made of the following principal
			components.
		</para>

		<section id="dashboard">
			<title>Dashboard</title>
			<para>
				The dashboard is the UI where all the dashboard queries
				are rendered.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="dashboard_queries_engine">
			<title>Dashboard Queries</title>
			<para>
				The dashboard queries are the core of the engines and
				query the database to provide snapshots of the actual
				data. These are entities that contain the query and the
				format of the rendered output such as a bar chart or pie
				chart.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="reports_engine">
			<title>Reports Engine</title>
			<para>
				JBoss BAM allows the integration of reporting tools
				through the integration of reporting engines. Currently
				Jasper Reports is shipped with the solution and provides
				the end-users the option of building their own reports
				and integrate them with the solution.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="alert_engine">
			<title>Alert Engine</title>
			<para>
				The alert engines is a core component of the system that
				provides a methodology of sending a alert or
				notification through a number of patterns. This engine
				is still under-construction and will initially support
				the communication of alert throughout email, future
				notifications will be enabled through different
				protocols such as SMS, Blackburry, etc...
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
					This is component is still under construction.
				</para>
			</note>
		</section>

		<section id="rules_engine">
			<title>Rules Engines</title>
			<para>
				The rules engine is the bridge between the Alert Engine
				and the Dashboard Queries Engine. This components links
				notifications to queries in the sense that whenever a
				query returns a result that meets a rule, then the
				appropriate alert from the alert_engine is triggered to
				notify the destination personnel of the action to
				execute. are rendered.
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
					This is component is still under construction.
				</para>
			</note>
		</section>

	</section>

</chapter>
